A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, Corporation, Board of Trustees, Committees FA860
Rockefeller Archive Center
The members of the original Board of Directors became the Board of Scientific Directors and remained unchanged except that in 1911 Theodore C. Janeway was elected to fill the vacancy created by the death of Christian A. Herter. T.C. Janeway died in 1918 and until 1920 the Board of Scientific Directors consisted of only six members. In 1920 W.J.V. Osterhout was added to the Board. In 1923 Hermann M. Biggs died, and in 1924 both L. Emmett Holt and T. Mitchell Prudden died. Francis Gilman Blake and John Howland were named in 1924 to fill two of the vacancies. In 1925 W.J.V. Osterhout resigned to join the scientific staff of the Institute and in 1926 Charles R. Stockard was elected to fill this vacancy. In 1926 Francis W. Peabody was elected to succeed T. Mitchell Prudden but he died less than a year later. John Howland died in 1926, and Eugene L. Opie, elected to fill that vacancy served on the Board of Scientific Directors 1929-1932. In 1930 James B. Conant was elected to fill the vacancy created by the death of Francis W. Peabody. William H. Welch resigned in 1933 and Warfield T. Longcope was elected to that vacancy in 1934. Theobald Smith died in 1934. In 1935 A. Raymond Dochez was elected to succeed Francis G. Blake, and in October of that same year Herbert S. Gasser succeeded Simon Flexner as Director of the Institute and on the Board of Scientific Directors. In 1936 Walter B. Cannon and George H. Whipple were elected to the Board. Charles Rupert Stockard died in 1939 and was succeeded by Ross G. Harrison. Walter B. Cannon died in 1945 and was succeeded in 1946 by Detlev W. Bronk. James B. Conant resigned in 1949 and Vincent du Vigneaud was elected to that vacancy. Warfield T. Longcope resigned in 1952.
The original elected officers of the Board of Scientific Directors were William H. Welch, President; T. Mitchell Prudden, Vice-President; and L. Emmett Holt, Secretary. In 1924 Theobald Smith was elected Vice-President and Francis G. Blake, Secretary. In 1933, Theobald Smith was elected President and Charles R. Stockard, Vice-President. Charles R. Stockard was elected President and A. Raymond Dochez, Secretary in 1935- The office of Vice-President was not filled until 1937 when Warfield T. Longcope was elected Vice-President. Warfield T. Longcope became President in 1939 and in 1940 Ross G. Harrison became Vice-president. In 1952 when Warfield T. Longcope resigned from the Board of Scientific Directors, Ross G. Harrison was elected President; A. Raymond Dochez, Vice-President and Vincent du Vigneaud, Secretary.
William H. Welch and Simon Flexner were the original representatives of the Board of Scientific Directors on the Board of Trustees. When Simon Flexner retired as Director of The Institute he was succeeded on the Board of Trustees by Herbert S. Gasser, and in 1936 Charles R. Stockard was appointed to succeed the late William H. Welch. In 1939 Charles R. Stockard was succeeded by George H. Whipple.
In 1953 an extensive reorganization began. The Rules for the Board of Scientific Directors were repealed. New By-Laws for the Corporation provided that the members of the Board of Scientific Directors as constituted on June 23, 1953, and the members of the Board of Trustees on that same date, merge to form one Board known as the Board of Trustees.
Governing Boards of The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, 1901-1911, from information in the Minutes of the Board of Scientific Directors, May 1901-June 1911 (The first minutes of the Board of Trustees are dated 17 October 1910)
24 June 1901 Board of Directors; William H. Welch, President; T. Mitchell Prudden, Vice President; Christian A. Herter, Treasurer; L. Emmett Holt, Secretary; Hermann M. Biggs; Simon Flexner; Theobald Smith
12 April 1902 Directors Flexner and Holt, elected for three years to succeed themselves. Officers of previous year re-elected.
11 April 1903 Directors Herter and Smith, elected for three years to succeed themselves. Officers of previous year re-elected.
13 June 1904 Directors Biggs, Prudden, and Welch, elected for three years to succeed themselves. Officers of previous year re-elected.
15 April 1905 Directors Holt and Flexner, elected for three years to succeed themselves. Officers of previous year re-elected. New officer: "Directors of Laboratories - Dr. Simon Flexner."
21 April 1906 Directors Smith and Herter, elected for three years to succeed themselves. Officers of previous year re-elected.
13 April 1907 Directors Welch, Biggs, and Prudden, elected for three years to succeed themselves. Officers of previous year re-elected
11 April 1908 Directors Flexner and Holt, elected for three years to succeed themselves. Officers of previous year re-elected.
10 April 1909 Directors Smith and Herter, elected for three years to succeed themselves. Officers Welch, Prudden, and Flexner re-elected. L. Emmett Holt, Secretary and Treasurer. New Officer: "Director of the Hospital - Dr. Rufus I. Cole."
9 April 1910 Directors Welch, Prudden, and Biggs, elected for three years to succeed themselves. Officers of previous year re-elected.
15 October 1910 Board of Directors adopts new By-laws, establishing Board of Trustees, to consist of not more than 9 members, and Board of Scientific Directors, to consist of not more than 7 members.
First Board of Trustees: William H. Welch, Frederick T. Gates, Simon Flexner, Starr J. Murphy, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
First Board of Scientific Directors: Simon Flexner, L. Emmett Holt, Theobald Smith, Christian A. Herter, William H. Welch, T. Mitchell Prudden, Hermann Biggs.
21 January 1911 Recorded as "Regular Quarterly Meeting of the Board of Directors."
8 April 1911 Recorded as "Regular Quarterly Meeting of the Board of Scientific Directors."
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 130-8
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for scholarly research.
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Gates, Frederick Taylor; Rockefeller University
- Building Committee, 1909-1931, 1949; 1 box (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Papers: minutes, notes, charts, estimates, summaries and correspondence.
  Includes minutes of meetings of Building Committee, duplicates of correspondence, correspondence with contractors, correspondence with Starr J. Murphy regarding expenditure authorizations for placing contracts and acceptance of bids. Also correspondence with architects. Some material from the Princeton Improvement Committee. Includes some drawings, working papers and handwritten notes.
  Also material used showing need of additional endowment.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged in chronological order.; Hospital construction filed separately.
  - Material regarding hospital construction, 1909-1910; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Records and material showing change of the original building plan from the idea of adding wings to the first laboratory building to separate buildings., 1910-1914 (Box 1)
  - Letter (copy) to Starr J. Murphy "Notes on Present Buildings, NY" for presentation to the Rockefeller Foundation, June 28, 1916 attached to a compilation of supporting data, 1916 June 23 (Box 1)
  - Compilation of data dated April 30, 1914-Nov. 23, 1917 dealing with Endowment and Capital Expenditures for the Department of Animal Pathology, 1917 December 11 (Box 1)
  - Exterior Street elevation (Coolidge, Shepley, Bulfinch and Abbott, architects) of proposed building plans, 1928 June 31 (Box 1)
- Committee papers, 1953-1958 (Box 2)
  - Committee on Business Operations, 1953-1957 (Box 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Meetings and reports of committee to investigate accouting methods and procedures as per changes suggested by Ernst & Ernst, including letters from Charles Petrzelka, Bursar. Report from Detlev Bronk to Douglas Whitaker (including handwritten first draft). Analysis of appropriations, 1953-1958. Includes study done by Cresap, McCormick and Peget, Reconnaissance Report: Business Management, Organization, Objectives and Policies, December 1953.
  - Meetings and Reports, 1956-1957 (Box 2)
    Committee reports to investigate: Obsolescence Fund; Insurance Fire Loss Reserve; Pension Fund; Workmen's Compensation Insurance Fund.
    With correspondence from Roger C. Elliot reporting on progress in setting up Major Medical Insurance Plan.
  - Committee on Educational Policies, 1957-1958 (Box 2)
    Includes a report to the Committee comprised of: 1. A list of students and their advisors. 2. Description of student-faculty conference. 3. Notes from the Dean of Graduate Studies on evolution of the program. 4. Description of the seminars and courses offered in 1958.
  - Committee on Hospital Affairs, 1957-1958 (Box 2)
    Summary of conditions under study, in-patients, out-patients, patient per physician (in-patient), cost of patient care.
- Committee on Nomination and Review, 1951 December-1953 June; 1 box (2 1/2 inches)
  Biographical/Historical note
  The Committee on Nomination and Review was chosen by the Board of Trustees and the Board of Scientific Directors at a meeting on 26 October 1951 to nominate a director to succeed Dr. Herbert S. Gasser who was scheduled to retire in June 1953. In its deliberations the Committee was asked to review the fundamental policies of the Institute.
  Committee members were: Detlev W. Bronk, Chairman; Donald K. David; A. Raymond Dochez, M.D.; Barklie Henry; Lindsley F. Kimball, M.D.; David Rockefeller, ex officio; George H. Whipple, M.D.
  Additional people attending some or all meetings were Warren Lindquist, secretary; W.F. Loomis, consultant; John Lockwood and Thomas M. Debevoise, counsels.
  Meetings were held between December 1951 and October 1952. The nomination of Detlev Bronk for the position of Director had been determined by the Annual meeting of October 1952 though no announcement was to be made until June 1953 at which time final report was to be made.
  Loomis diaries.
  The papers consist of records of the deliberations. They are arranged in 11 folders. Also included is a mimeographed copy of Herbert S. Gasser's "Supplement to the Report to the Members of the Corporation" 1951 October 26.
  Arranged by subject.
  - Loomis diaries, 1952 January 15-May 1; p. 17-94, (p. 1-16 missing) (Box 3, Folder 1)
    These comprise a running log of interviews conducted with leaders in medical research soliciting opinions on the place of the RIMR for the future. The pages are numbered consecutively though interviews were conducted over a period of time and copies were sent to committee members in portions, with a covering letter.
    Included are 11 pages of suggestions and observations extracted from the Loomis diaries annotated as to page and source.
  - Replies to David Rockefeller letter of 1952 April 11 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    A letter was sent to Members of The Rockefeller Institute soliciting opinions and suggestions for possible candidates as Director as well as directions for development. Replies are alphabetically arranged: Archibald, R.M.; Braun, Armin C.; Craig, Lyman C.; Dole, Vincent; Dubos, Rene; Goebel, Walther; Granick, Sam; Holmes, F.O.; Horsfall, F.L.; Kunitz, Moses; Kunke, Henry; Lancefield, R.; Lloyd, D.P.C.; Longsworth, L.; McCarty, M.; McMaster, P.; Moore, S.; Nelson, J.B.; Northrop, J.H.; Olitsky, P.; Porter, K.R.; Rivers, T.M.; Stein, W.H.; Stoll, Norman; Trager, W.; Van Slyke, D.D. (emeritus) carbon copy; Woolley, D.W.
  - Summaries of Committee meetings (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Includes covering letter from Warren T. Lindquist 1953 January 9.
    Includes a set of ribbon copies and set of 1st carbon copies.
    Also includes "Eight alternatives to present pattern" (2nd meeting) and "Nine conclusions reached at 3rd meeting and reaffirmed at 4th meeting and five additional conclusions reached at 4th meeting".
    - Agenda of Committee meetings, 1951 December 10
    - Review of present patterns and alternatives, 1952 January 18
    - Draft of conclusions, 1952 March 25
    - Nomination of Detlev W. Bronk, 1952 April 22
    - Preliminary draft of report, 1952 May 21
    - Draft of new By-Laws, 1952 June 24
    - Reaffirm nomination of D.W. Bronk, 1952 October 31
  - Correspondence and notes (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - David Rockefeller to Detlev Bronk, 1952 April 24
      Enclosing copy of letter from John Lockwood on relationship of Board of Trustees to Board of Scientific Directors. This was written after April 22 meeting which nominated D.W. Bronk as Director. Handwritten note by David Rockefeller added.
    - Tentative outline of position for Nomination Committee at Annual Meeting regarding the nomination of D.W. Bronk with the understanding of his unavailability until June 1954
      Includes 6 pages of handwritten notes by D.W. Bronk on conditions for his acceptance.
    - G letter from D.W. Bronk to David Rockefeller, 1952 October 2
      3 page carbon copy itemizing his feelings regarding his obligations to The Johns Hopkins and the effect on his relation to the RIMR. Includes 1 folded page of handwritten notes by Dr. Bronk written on the evening of October 30 and read to the Special Committee the morning of October 31 and a second page of handwritten notes written as an addendum immediately following the Special Committee meeting on October 1952.
  - Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - W. "Farnie" Loomis to D.W. Bronk resigning as secretary of the Committee as of the 30th of June since work of Committee is "essentially finished", 1952 June 30
    - John E. Lockwood to D.W. Bronk enclosing a new set of By-Laws merging the Board of Trustees and the Board of Scientific Directors, 1952 July 10; 3 page typescript signed
    - Richard Shope to D.W. Bronk on the need for a mechanism by which differences between scientific staff and administration can be considered in a democratic fashion, 1952 November 24; 2 page typescript signed
    - Rafael [Lorente de No] to D.W. Bronk on change of planned resignation from the RIMR, 1952 December 6; Holograph
  - Summary of meeting of the Special Committee, 1953 January 22; 2 copies (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Covering letter from Warren T. Lindquist to Detlev W. Bronk as Chairman of the Committee and draftsman of the Committee report.
    Included are: five pages of handwritten notes used by Dr. Bronk in a presentation and which are intended to serve as Appendix I [typescript translation]; 1/23/1953 draft of new by-laws to serve as Appendix II and mimeographed minutes of 22 January 1953 Executive Committee meeting of the Board of Trustees forming Appendix III.
  - By-Laws, 1953 May 20 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Draft of By-Laws with 1953 May 20 covering letter from John Lockwood to D.W. Bronk. Changes suggested by David Rockefeller deal with Chairman of the Board, President and a Director.
    Includes 3 pages of handwritten notes by D.W. Bronk dealing with possible conflict inherent in suggested organization.
  - Further revision of By-Laws, 1953 June 4 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Covering memo from T.M. Debevoise and John E. Lockwood to members of the Nomination Committee clarifying changes.
  - Procedures for adoption of new by-laws, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    1953 June 5 and 1953 June 15 letters from J.E. Lockwood to D.W. Bronk dealing with procedures and resolutions to be presented for adoption at meeting of the Corporation on 23 June 1953.
  - Press releases (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Draft of release announcing retirement of Herbert S. Gasser as Institute Director, 1953 June 21
    - Draft of release announcing appointment of Detlev W. Bronk as Director, 1953 June 24
    - Covering letter from F.A. Jamieson, 1953 June 18
  - Elections (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Letter from Edric B. Smith to Detlev W. Bronk: notice of election as President of The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, 1953 July 10
    - Letters to Detlev W. Bronk, 1953 July 9
      With background material for presentation to Executive Committee at meeting on 1953 July 17 for Membership appointment of Frank Brink and H.K. Hartline.
- Property Management Committee, 1970 December 8-1974 June; 1 box (2 1/2 inches)
  Between December 1970 and June 1974 a committee (Property Management Committee) representing the University administration as well as the Board of Trustees dealt with the problems of management of three off-campus properties: Socony Hall, City Block, Sutton Terrace.
  Members of the committee were: C.E. Sunderlin, Chairman, Jack Contes, Roger Elliot, Paul Penndorf, Sydney Woodd-Cahousac, Richard Dana, Secretary, John Schnauffer, legal consultant.
  Minutes of meetings.
  Fifty-seven meetings were held; with the minutes for each meeting there may be various tables or collected information for consideration at the stated meeting.
  Arranged in chronological order.
  - Meeting 1-17 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Meeting 18-35 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Meeting 36-48 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Meeting 49-57 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Committee files, 1981-1984
  - Ad Hoc Committee on Industrial Sponsorship of Research, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Standing Committee on Scientific Affairs, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Joint Meeting of Building & Real Estate Committee and Ad Hoc Committee on Scholars Residence, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Ad Hoc Committee on University-Industry Relations, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Standing Committee on University Affairs, 1972
  In 1972 the Standing Committee on University Affairs (SCUA) to foster broader communication among all facets of the University community was established. It is made up of two representatives from each of the following: Trustees, Tenured faculty, Non tenured faculty, Administration, and Graduate students. The first chairman was Walter N. Rothschild, Jr., a member of the Board of Trustees.
  The project for 1973 was a planned experiment to serve in an advisory capacity on a few selected investment issues of major ethical concern. Alan M. Tartakoff serves as the principal representative in collecting information pertinent to those proxies selected for the experiment.
  - Correspondence, 1972 November-December (Box 6)
    Letter from Rodney Nichols to Albert Gold on matter of a Day-Care Center in the new faculty housing in recognition of the needs of the women working at RU. Includes numbers of children in various RU families.